What we're looking for is how everything works
What makes everything work
It has to do with curiosity.
It has to do with people wondering
what makes something do something?
There's a way of looking anew
As if you never saw it before the first time and asking questions about it as if you were different
And then to discover that if you try to get answers then that we made it return
The things that make the wind, make the waves.
The motion of water, is like the motion of air,
is like the motion of sand
Things have common features
It turns out more and more universal
It's almost unbelievable
The truth is so remarkable, so amazing
It's incredible
Take the world from another point of view
It's curiosity
It's the way who we are, what we are
Just like a runner gets a kick out of sweating
I get a kick out of thinking
I can't stop
It's curiosity