We're going on a journey.
This video depicts billion years of time unfolding
on a 10 minute scale - from to Big Bang to today.
Every passing second represents 22 million years.
On this scale, humans do not appear until the last fraction of second.
The universe begins in 5.....
The universe begins in 4....
The universe begins in 3...
The universe begins in 2..
The universe begins in 1.
The Universe Has Begin!!!
[The Big Bang]
[The First Star]
Brian: From the primordial cloud of gas and cosmic dust
gravity forged the stars.
[Early Star Formation]
[Early galaxy formation]
Gravity connects star systems
together in vast galaxies
[Early galaxy formation]
together in vast galaxies,
and steers them
in their journey through unbounded space.
The relentless flow of time
has driven the evolution of the universe
and created extraordinary wonders.
Some galaxies formed so close together
that they are locked
in a gravitational embrace.
What a magnificent sight it will be!
As it evolves the universe
passes through distinct eras,
vast ages whose beginnings and endings
are marked by unique milestones,
the births and deaths of its wonders.
Carl: We're the product of a grand evolutionary sequence.
Cosmic evolution.
About which we are only occasionally aware.
[Milky Way Formation]
Brian: Gravity is the great creator,
the constructor of worlds.
But gravity is also the destroyer,
because it's relentless.
[Black Hole Formation]
When a star around 15 times
the mass of our Sun collapses,
all the matter in it's core is crushed
into an infinite void of blackness,
know as Stellar Mass Black Hole.
The immense gravitational pull of
these monsters can rip a star apart.
They tear matter from its surface,
and drag it into orbit.
This super-heated matter spins
around the mouth of the black hole,
and great jets of radiation fire from the core.
Although these jets can be seen across the cosmos,
the core itself remains a mystery.
Not even light can escape,
so their interior is forever hidden from us.
[Star Death and Rebirth]
Throughout the stars life,
there's a constantly battle
between energy pushing out and gravity pushing in.
When it runs out of fuel,
the star collapses
and then explodes with
the brightness of a billion of suns.
As the star is torn apart,
it will fire out into space
all the elements that it created on it's life
and death.
These are new stars,
forming from the elements
blown out by supernova explosions.
New stars being born,
from the remains of dead ones.
And it's from this universal process of death,
and rebirth
that we emerged.
Because it was in a nebula just like this
5 billion years ago
that our Sun was formed.
[Collapse of Protoplantary Dust Cloud]
Clouds of hydrogen collapses
further and further onto the force of gravity
and the life cycle of a new star has begun.
A star was born,
that would come to be known,
as the Sun.
[Birth of the Sun]
Around it,
a network of planets formed,
among them,
was the Earth.
[Formation of Earth]
Debris left over the formation
of the Solar System
collides with the Earth.
[Formation of the Moon]
[Hadean Eon]
Earth, began life as a molten hell.
David: The early continents was still forming.
[Archean Eon]
The land was dominated by volcanoes
hostile and lifeless.
But deep in the oceans,
life had begun.
[Early Life Forms]
The latest theory is that chemicals,
spewing from underwater volcanic vents
solidified and created the conditions needed
for the first cells to form.
For some 3 billion years
simple, microscopic organisms
were the most advanced form of life on the planet.
Cyanobacteria and other oxygen
producing microbes began to blue.
[Oxygenation of Atmosphere]
These flourished in colonies of plant like
microbes that pumped out
enormous volumes of oxygen.
And was this increasing oxygen
that was the key for the rise
of the animal kingdom.
[Complex Single Celled Life]
Brian: Organisms started to produce oxygen to respire.
You will need of a lot more energy
which allows the development of more complex life.
[Proterozoic Eon]
David: Just before complex life appeared,
the world was in the grip of the
[Snowball Earth]
biggest ice age in its entire history.
[First Multicelled Animals]
And then suddenly,
advanced organisms have appeared.
[First Multicelled Animals]
[Cambrian Explosion]
[Ordovician Period]
[Silurian Period]
[Devonian Period]
[Carboniferous Period]
[Permian Period]
[Triassic Period]
[Cretaceous Period]
[Rise of Mammals]
[Audstralopithecus Afarensis]
[Homo Erectus]
[Neanderthals]
[Homo Sapiens]
[Homo Nouveau]
Timelapse Of The Entire Universe
Crafted by Melodysheep
For more about his video, visit
melodysheep.com/timelapse